Xu Xian had just received yet
another invitation
to the opening ceremony of the new
Jin Shan Temple.
His wife, Bai Su Zhen,
had warned him not to attend.
Since she was in fact a benevolent /bɪˈnevələnt  仁慈的/ white
snake spirit in human form,
their marriage had already weathered /weðəd 风华/
attacks by meddling /ˈmedəl 管闲事/ monks.
But devout /dɪˈvaʊt 虔诚的/ Buddhist /ˈbʊdɪst/ that he was,
Xu Xian felt obligated /ˈɒblɪˌɡeɪt 有责任的/ to make
an appearance.
What they didn’t know
was that these invitations had come
from none other than Fa Hai–
the misguided /ˌmɪsˈɡaɪdɪd/ monk who had
tried to separate the young lovers,
almost killing Xu Xian in the process.
The monk confronted Xu Xian,
telling him that because he consorted /ˈkɒnsɔːt （使）陪伴/
with a demon,
he must remain at the monastery /ˈmɒnəstərɪ 修道院/
and cleanse his soul.
Xu Xian protested,
but Fa Hai would not let him escape.
At home, Bai Su Zhen was uneasy.
Her husband had departed so quickly
that she hadn’t been able to tell him
she was pregnant /ˈpreɡnənt/ with his child.
And now he had been gone so long
she sensed /sensd/ something must be wrong.
She made her way to the temple,
and upon encountering Fa Hai
the monk threw his prayer mat /mæt 席子/,
which erupted /ɪˈrʌpt 爆发/ into fire and smoke.
Weakened from her pregnancy /ˈpreɡnənsi/,
Bai Su Zhen desperately /ˈdespərətlɪ 绝拼命地/ summoned /ˈsʌmən 召唤/  a fleet
of shrimp soldiers and crab generals
to subdue /səbˈdjuː 压制/ the monk,
and waves to put out the blaze /bleɪz 烈火/.
But the water also flooded the
surrounding area,
drowning /draʊn 淹没/ many innocent villagers.
For the first time, Bai Su Zhen had
harmed humans,
and she fell out of the gods’ favor.
With their blessing /bles 祝福/ retracted /rɪˈtrækt 撤回/,
Fa Hai attempted to trap her
in his magical alms /ɑːmz 救济金/ bowl.
But just when all hope seemed lost,
a bright glow /ɡləʊ 红光/ came from within her belly /ˈbeli 腹部/,
saving her from the mad monk’s magic.
The couple fled /flee 过去/ home,
grateful to the mysterious /mɪˈstɪərɪəs/ power
that had saved them,
and soon after, Bai Su Zhen gave
birth to their son, Xu Shi Lin.
Yet despite this joyous /ˈdʒɔɪəs 快乐的/occasion,
Xu Xian was uneasy.
He was shaken by his wife’s accidental
act of destruction,
and he feared the misfortune /ˌmɪsˈfɔːtʃuːn 灾祸/
it might bring upon their home.
Not a month later,
Fa Hai appeared at their doorstep.
He offered Xu Xian an alms /ɑːmz 救济金/ bowl to
ensure good fortune for his newborn son.
Still wary /ˈweərɪ 谨慎的/ of the monk,
but also remembering Bai Su Zhen’s
destructive act,
Xu Xian accepted the gift.
But as soon as the bowl
entered their home,
it flew to Bai Su Zhen’s head
and trapped her inside.
Against the family’s wishes,
Fa Hai buried /ˈberi/ the bowl beneath
the Lei Feng Pagoda /pəˈɡəʊdə 佛塔/.
And when Xu Xian begged him to
release his wife,
the monk sternly /ˈstɜːnlɪ 严厉地/ replied:
“She will be free when the
iron tree blooms.”
Overcome with guilt,
Xu Xian ran away to a monastery /ˈmɒnəstri 僧侣/,
leaving Shi Lin in the care of his aunt /ɑːnt 阿姨/.
But there was something neither
of them knew.
The boy was the reincarnation /ˌriːɪnkɑːˈneɪʃən 转世/
of Wen Qu Xing,
the wisdom /ˈwɪzdəm 智慧/ god,
sent to the family to reward
Xu Xian’s devotion /dɪˈvəʊʃn 献身/.
It was this power that had protected
Bai Su Zhen at the temple,
and as he grew, so did his wisdom.
At age 19, Shi Lin went to the capital
city to take the nation-wide imperial /ɪmˈpɪərɪəl 帝国的/ exam
and obtained the highest score
in all the empire.
The Emperor himself bestowed /bɪˈstəʊ 授予/
Shi Lin’s prize:
an ornate /ɔːˈneɪt 装饰华丽的/ hat decorated with
jewel-encrusted /ɪnˈkrʌstɪd 外壳的/ flowers.
But though he returned home in glory /ˈɡlɔːri 光荣/,
the fate /feɪt 命运/ of his parents still
weighed heavy on his mind.
Coaxing /kəʊks 哄/ his father from exile /ˈɛɡzaɪl 流放/,
Shi Lin took him to visit the Lei Feng
Pagoda /pəˈɡəʊdə 佛塔/ to pay respects to his mother.
Kneeling before it,
he placed his jeweled prize on the
iron tree as an offering.
Suddenly, the ground opened and
Bai Su Zhen stepped out.
With her sins /sɪn 犯罪/ absolved /əbˈzɒlv 免除/ by
the tribute /ˈtrɪbjuːt 礼物/ of a god,
and a blossom /ˈblɒsəm 花/ on the iron tree,
Shi Lin had freed his mother,
and reunited his family–
both mortal and divine /dɪˈvaɪn 神圣的/.
i wish we could be trees deep in the mountains, touching, twining /twaɪn 缠绕/ limb around limb /lɪm 树枝/